And welcome to another walkthrough for computer
Architecture for everybody. In this walkthrough,
We're going to cover the gates, the gate layout
System and the gate simulation system. It has an
Extensive help, probably more than you need
If you get stuck or you want to paste some of
This stuff into AI and figure out how to how
To use it. So, I'm just going to walk through
The basic features. So we have a wide range of
Components all the way from something as simple
As a single and gate or an input or an output
That we can put in or we can put something much
More simpler like a Nixie display right so if we
Take this Nixie display and you can drag things
Around and you can connect them to the input
And so this is the Nixie display that's got a
One two and four input so let's play with that a
Little bit give ourselves another input oops click
To connect them and Then so so you so I've got
This Nixie input. It's a three because it's a one
And a one. So it's a one. the two input is one
And the one input is one. Let's go ahead and bring
Another input in and connect it. Oops. Connect.
Connect. There we go. So now it is a seven. Right.
So this is a Nixie. You can do some practice.
So that's a a four and a two and a zero which
Is a six. And you can rename these things. So I'm
Going to call this I'm going to call this one ones
And I'm going call this one twos. So this little
Tag you can tag and then click on something and
Then fours. So we can have the bits for the
Ones, twos, and fours. And if we turn it off,
Then that's going to be a two. So that's a two.
If I add one to that, then that's three. And so
That's a And you can just build these little
Circuits., so one of the things that I'll
Just show you that is really weird is there's an
Automatic layout. So like, so like if I had to
Put this input over here,, it's trying its
Hardest. Laying out circuits is a hard thing.
And I've got it using spline curves. But if you
Come over and you highlight and double click,
You will create what's called a waypoint. And then
I can I can route these wires creatively
And then drag these waypoints. It doesn't change
The circuits at all. And so I can make this look
A little bit better using way points. Okay. and
So couple other things. Let's see. we can get a
Component, a full ladder component. So, it's carry
In, an A and a B, and then a sum and a carry out.
And that is,, inside of that, inside of
Every one of these are transistors. And Nixie tube
Has got some glowing stuff. It's it's actually a
Tube. I just put it in because it's pretty., we
Got a JK flip-flop, which and so a JK flip-flop.
, I'll go through this in a little bit more.
We've got even a thing called a three-bit latch,
Which we'll use later as a register. It has some
Inputs and outputs and it has an internal state
And the pulsing on the clock copies the input
Into the internal state. Then letting go of the
Clock will copy the internal state to the output
And we have a three bit adder that takes A and B
In the ones, twos and fours column and then the
Sum comes out. And so that is basically the kinds
Of things that you can can do. And remember that
Every one of these things eventually turns into
Transistors. Okay, so let's I showed you the tag.
The tag you just grab something and then fun and
You just give it a name. And so that gives these
Things names. You can delete something by clicking
The little trash can icon and then highlighting an
Item and it deletes it. And if you click and
Delete something that has a wire associated
With it, it can deletes the wire as well., you
Can save a circuit stuff and it saves the circuit
Inside your browser in what's called local storage
In your browser and then you can load it. So,
If you're in the middle of working on something
And you want to save it and load it, well,
Let let me do this. I'm going to clear all of
Them. Clear everything. Get rid of everything.
And now I can reload that circuit from the storage
That was called stuff. It was a crazy circuit.
So, I just loaded stuff back up. And so, that
Was that circuit. I saved it. I loaded it. You
Could load it. You could add a thing. We
Could Let's add another input. And then
Connect it up and then save it as stuff again.
Save. Okay. Now, let's clear everything again
And then load stuff back up. And you should see
And it's edited. See, I can I can load it. I can
Edit it and then save it and then load it again.
And so if you if you are to go and relaunch
This, I'll just refresh the page and you'll
See what happens here. It's gone. That's all
Just in the browser storage. But if you were
Clever enough to save it, you can load it back up.
So again, depending on how complex the work that
You're going to do, you can use load and save.
So let's go through a couple of other things.
They like I mentioned, if you if you're
Trying to like make the wires route nicely,
You can double click on the line and
Create a waypoint. And I don't know why,
But I have a thing to hide the waypoints if you
Don't want to see them and then show them back.
There's also a command down here, and that's
Described in the help documentation. So you can
Say place NAND and so it'll put a NAND in there
If you really want to read the instructions.,
And I did this to some degree for accessibility
Where you can,, place a NAND and give it
A name and then you can connect the output
Of the NAND to the input of something.,
We'll see how well people find that to use.
I put it in there. I may have to work on it
And improve it over time, but you can show and
Hide. You can show and hide the command line
Interface. I hope that this basic walkthrough of
The gates layout tool has been helpful to you.